Guide to the The Walter G. Davis Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Goodwin Davis papers
1918-1919
MS 469
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Correspondence, notes, and other papers, including a diary, of Walter G. Davis, Assistant Military Attaché at Berne in 1918. After the November armistice he was attached to the American Commission to Negotiate Peace in Paris. He was also a member of the Coolidge Mission to Austria-Hungary until March, 1919.
Davis, Walter Goodwin, 1885-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter G. Davis in 1958.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Davis Papers comprise 16 folders (contained in one box) that include (a) notes, memoranda and various other items connected with his stay in Berne; and (b) a limited amount of correspondence and a copy of the personal diary which Davis kept in the course of his fact-finding tour with the Coolidge Mission.
Biographical / Historical
Walter Goodwin Davis was born in Portland, Maine, on May 24, 1885. He attended Exeter and received his B.A., Yale in 1908 (along with Charles Seymour and Gordon Auchincloss). After completing his law studies at Harvard (LL.B. '11) he joined the firm of Shearman and Sterling in New York. Subsequently he returned to Portland where he pursued a business and banking career. In the meantime, following the American declaration of war against German in April 1917, Davis attended Officers Training Camp at Plattsburg and received a commission as Captain of Infantry in early 1918. He was assigned to the Military Intelligence Service, and served as Assistant Military Attache at Berne, with occasional duty at General Headquarters in Chaumont. After the November armistice he was attached to the American Commission to Negotiate Peace in Paris, subsequently being transferred to Vienna as a member of the Coolidge Mission, where he remained until March 1919.
World War, 1914-1918; United States -- Foreign relations; Diplomats; Davis, Walter Goodwin, 1885-1966; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Parker, Franklin Ellsworth, 1861-; Paris Peace Conference. United States Territorial Section ( 1919-1920. United States Territorial Section) -- 1919-1920
- Inventory
  - General Correspondence (1919 Jan-Mar)
    - Dulles, Allen [and Charles Seymour] [7 items] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Goodwin, Phillip [1 item] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - King, Frederic [1 item] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lubomirska, Princess [1 item] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nolan, General [1 item] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Parker, Franklin E. [1 item] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda and Notes (1918 Aug-Dec)
    - Office of the Military Attache: organizational and routine matters, 1918 Aug, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda on coordination of counter-intelligence reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Memoranda to Lt. Col. Godson, 1918 September-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous memoranda on military intelligence (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memorandum on Propaganda, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda on repatriation of P.O.W.'s, 1918 Oct, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The "Von Rechtman" reports [Mme Styschinska], 1918 March-November (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal and Memorabilia
    - Newspaper clippings [Swiss and French], 1918 November (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Photos, and [printed] List of Berne Diplomatic Corps, 1918 March (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Personal Diary, 116 pp., 1918 December 20-1919 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)